Guide to the Bingham Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Hiram Bingham III, Elihu Yale biography, 1671-1939; 1937-1939; Series VIII; 3; (7 boxes)
  - Writings of Hiram Bingham III
    - Research material
      - Auction catalogues of Elihu Yale's collection; British Museum (photostatic copies) (Box 92, Folder 41)
      - "The Weekly Journal," "The Daily Courant," 1721; British Museum (photostatic copies) (Box 92, Folder 42)
      - "The Daily Post," "The Daily Courant," 1722; British Museum (photostatic copies) (Box 92, Folder 43)
      - "The Daily Courant," 1723; British Museum (photostatic copies) (Box 92, Folder 44)
      - Society for the Propagation of the Gospel, documents, 1717 (photostatic copies) (Box 92, Folder 45)
      - Diary, 1693, from the Lambeth Palace Library (photostatic copies) (Box 92, Folder 46)
      - Public Record Office documents (photostatic copies) (Box 92, Folder 47)
      - Massachusetts Historical Society documents (photostatic copies) (Box 92, Folder 48)
      - Chester City Record Office, documents (photostatic copies) (Box 92, Folder 49)
      - Articles on Elihu Yale (photostatic copies) (Box 92, Folder 50)
      - Articles concerning the East India Company and schools (photostatic copies) (Box 92, Folder 51)
      - Ezra Stiles' diary (photostatic copies) (Box 92, Folder 52)
      - Printed articles, 1903, 1937 (Box 92, Folder 53)
      - Oversize documents (photostatic copies) (Box 93, Folder 54)
    - Research notes
      - Elihu Yale chronology
        - 1671-1707 (Box 94, Folder 55-68)
        - 1708-1728 (Box 95, Folder 69-71)
      - Letters of Elihu Yale, 1687 July-December (Box 95, Folder 72)
      - Elihu Yale: "Daughters and sons-in-law, Dudley North and Lord James Cavendish" (Box 95, Folder 73)
      - Elihu Yale's gift to the College (Box 95, Folder 74)
      - Elihu Yale's estate: auction items (Box 95, Folder 75)
      - Elihu Yale's financial dealings (Box 95, Folder 76)
      - Elihu Yale's ancestral home (Box 95, Folder 77)
      - Yale family history (Box 95, Folder 78)
      - Maps of London, 1677, 1741-1745 (Box 95, Folder 79)
      - Research correspondence (Box 95, Folder 80)
      - Chronology (Box 95, Folder 81)
      - Bibliography compiled by Hiram Bingham III (Box 95, Folder 82)
      - Reference file (Box 95, Folder 83)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 95, Folder 84)
- Hiram Bingham III, Personal papers, 1875-1975; 1875-1957; Series IX; 3.5; (9 boxes)
  Diaries, Writings, Scrapbooks, Juvenilia, and Education are arranged chronologically. Biographical material, Family history, and Legal and financial are arranged by type of material. Clubs and organizations and Photographs are arranged by subject.
  Series IX, Hiram Bingham III, Personal papers, contains other papers of general biographical interest. Diaries consists of Bingham's diaries for the years 1905 to 1916 (one diary has notations extending to 1931); typewritten extracts from the diaries, 1910-1915, made by Woodbridge Bingham; and a notebook dated 1915-1916. Writings consists of Bingham's manuscripts, book reviews, articles, and speeches on subjects not related to Latin America, politics, aviation, or Elihu Yale. Scrapbooks consists of personal scrapbooks, dated 1880 and 1915-1917, a guest book, and newsclippings, 1897-1928. Biographical material contains materials of general biographical interest, including autobiographical statements, daily schedule records, diplomas and certificates, medical records, and obituaries. Family history consists of notes and partial drafts for Bingham's proposed biography of his grandfather, Hiram Bingham I; newsclippings and printed matter concerning Hawaii and the Bingham family; and genealogical material concerning the Bingham, Brewster, and Grant families. Juvenilia consists of Bingham's notes and letters, 1875-1883, and a book which he used as a child. Education consists of material relating to his studies at Oahu College, Phillips Academy, Yale, the University of California at Berkeley, and Harvard. Most of these papers are lecture notes and student essays. Clubs and organizations contains papers relating to various groups with which Bingham was associated, including one folder of materials concerning schools to which he considered sending his sons. General book circulars, invitations, menus, Christmas cards, and printed matter follow the alphabetical sequence of groups. Legal and financial comprises wills, legal agreements and papers, a small amount of financial correspondence, tax and insurance papers, account ledgers, bills and receipts, stocks and securities, and printed matter. The final section, Photographs, includes portraits of Hiram Bingham II, Hiram Bingham III, and other family members; photographs concerning aviation; and other miscellaneous subjects.
  - Diaries
    - 1905-1931 (Box 96, Folder 1-4)
    - Typewritten extracts, 1910-1915 (Box 96, Folder 5)
    - Notebooks, 1902-1904, 1915-1916 (Box 96, Folder 6)
  - Writings
    - Parables, 1898-1899 (Box 96, Folder 7)
    - "Five Straws from Revolutionary Fields", 1901 (Box 96, Folder 8)
    - Book reviews for "The Nation", 1914-1915 (Box 96, Folder 9)
    - "Problems of the Pacific", 1916 (Box 96, Folder 10)
    - "Yale in Public Life", 1916 (Box 96, Folder 10)
    - "Yale in Public Service", 1916 (Box 96, Folder 10)
    - Speeches, 1921-1923 (Box 96, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1880, 1915-1917 (Box 97, Folder 12-13)
    - Guest book, 1910, 1924, 1936 (Box 97, Folder 14)
    - Newsclippings, 1897-1928 (Box 97, Folder 15)
  - Biographical material
    - Autobiographical statements, Circa 1915 (Box 97, Folder 16)
    - Daily schedules and miscellaneous manuscripts, 1902-1915 (Box 97, Folder 17)
    - Diplomas, certificates (oversize) (Folder 115)
    - Medical records, 1954-1956 (Box 97, Folder 18)
    - Printed articles, 1923, 1925 (Box 97, Folder 19)
    - Obituaries, 1956 January (Box 97, Folder 20)
  - Family history
    - Notes and excerpts on life of Hiram Bingham I (Box 97, Folder 21)
    - Notes for a biography of Hiram Bingham I (Box 97, Folder 22)
    - Notes for a biography of Hiram Bingham I (Box 98, Folder 23-25)
    - Bingham and Brewster family records (photostatic copies) (Box 98, Folder 26)
    - Notes on Hawaiian commerce, arms and ammunition (Box 98, Folder 27)
    - Notes (Box 98, Folder 28-29)
    - Letters describing Bingham family history, 1930, 1957 (Box 98, Folder 30)
    - Newsclippings, 1900-1939 (Box 98, Folder 31-32)
    - Printed matter, 1884-1952 (Box 98, Folder 33-36)
      See also: Box 115
    - Bingham Day programs, 1975 (Box 99, Folder 37)
    - Inventory of Gilbertinia House (Box 99, Folder 38)
    - The Brewster family: genealogical material (Box 99, Folder 39)
    - The Grant family: genealogical material (Box 99, Folder 40)
  - Juvenilia
    - Notes and letters, 1875-1883 (Box 99, Folder 41)
    - The Queen of Picture Books for Boys and Girls (Box 99, Folder 42)
  - Education
    - Oahu College Rhetorical Exercises, 1890 (Box 99, Folder 43)
    - Phillips Academy Classical Department, 1893 (Box 99, Folder 43)
    - Yale College: lecture notes, English literature, 1895-1896 (Box 99, Folder 44)
    - Yale College: student essays, 1898 (Box 99, Folder 45)
    - University of California, Berkeley: Chapter of Hiram Bingham III's master's thesis, 1900 (Box 99, Folder 46)
    - Harvard University: lecture notes
      - Military history (Box 99, Folder 47)
      - International law, 1900-1901 (Box 99, Folder 48-50)
      - International law, 1901 (Box 100, Folder 51)
      - Harvard University: thesis on international law, 1901 April 29 (Box 100, Folder 52)
  - Clubs and organizations
    - Academy of Science (Box 100, Folder 53)
    - Advisory Committee on Archeology of Phillips Academy, 1913-1916 (Box 100, Folder 54)
    - Aero Club of America (Box 100, Folder 55)
    - American Antiquarian Society (Box 100, Folder 56)
    - American Geological Society (Box 100, Folder 56)
    - American Historical Association (Box 100, Folder 56)
    - Brick Row Print and Book Store, 1916 (Box 100, Folder 57)
    - Index Visible, 1916 (Box 100, Folder 57)
    - Cosmos Club (Box 100, Folder 58)
    - The Graduates Club (Box 100, Folder 59)
    - The University Club (Box 100, Folder 59)
    - Harvard Club (Box 100, Folder 60)
    - Libraries (Box 100, Folder 61)
    - Masonic lodges (Box 100, Folder 62)
    - New Haven organizations (Box 100, Folder 63)
    - The Rockefeller Foundation (Box 100, Folder 64)
    - Schools (Box 101, Folder 65)
    - Yale organizations (Box 101, Folder 66)
    - Book circulars (Box 101, Folder 67)
    - Invitations; menus; Christmas cards (Box 101, Folder 68)
    - Printed matter (Box 101, Folder 69-71)
  - Legal and financial
    - Wills, 1907-1909 (Box 102, Folder 72)
    - Court proceedings concerning will of Charles L. Tiffany, 1908-1909 (Box 102, Folder 73)
    - Legal agreements, 1900-1917 (Box 102, Folder 74)
    - Financial correspondence, 1913-1916 (Box 102, Folder 75)
    - Taxes, 1916-1919 (Box 102, Folder 76)
    - Insurance, 1908-1915 (Box 102, Folder 77)
    - Family ledger, 1909-1926 (Box 102, Folder 78)
    - Ledger, 1915-1916 (Box 102, Folder 79)
    - Special accounts: Lawrence Beebe, Kate Reynolds, Lydia Bingham Coan, Brewster Bingham, Tommy Davis, 1900-1916 (Box 102, Folder 80)
    - Bank accounts, 1915, 1922-1923 (Box 103, Folder 81)
    - Bills and receipts, 1903-1923 (Box 103, Folder 82-83)
    - Stocks and securities, 1876-1916 (Box 103, Folder 84)
    - Printed matter (Box 103, Folder 85-86)
  - Photographs
    - Hiram Bingham II and other family members (Box 103, Folder 87)
    - Portraits of Hiram Bingham III, 1876-1921 (Box 103, Folder 88-89)
    - Hiram Bingham III: family photographs (Box 103, Folder 90)
    - Group portraits including Hiram Bingham III (Box 103, Folder 91)
      - Oversize (Folder 115)
    - Aviation (Box 103, Folder 92)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 103, Folder 93)
      - Oversize (Folder 115)
    - Chiang Kai-shek, 1927 (Folder 103A)
      1 oval photograph (sepia), 27 x 21 cm. Framed 46 x 29 cm. Mat inscribed in Chinese characters by Chian Kai-shek for Hiram Bingham, summer 1927.
- Alfreda (Mitchell) Bingham, 1882-1976; Series X; 2.5; (6 boxes)
  The series is arranged by type of material.
  Series X, Alfreda M. Bingham, contains papers of Alfreda (Mitchell) Bingham and a small amount of material relating to her seven sons. There is a small amount of her personal correspondence here, although letters from Hiram Bingham and other family members are located with Family correspondence in Series III, and some letters addressed to Alfreda Bingham are in the General correspondence in Series III. A small amount of her correspondence and other personal papers dated before her first marriage is located in the Mitchell-Tiffany Family Papers (MS 701). This series also contains her writings (mostly poems and notes); her diaries from 1886 to 1946, including several early diaries written in German; appointment calendars, 1926-1933; books of souvenirs, autographs, notes, and addresses; her wedding invitation, 1900, and calling cards; concert programs; photographs; and newsclippings. Her financial records include account books, budget books, journal and payroll books, bills and receipts, a copy of her will, and notes concerning disposition of her property. Materials relating to her children include newsclippings, scrapbooks, school papers, and juvenilia. Of particular interest are several articles by Alfred M. Bingham, particularly "Sybil's Bones, a Chronicle of the Three Hiram Binghams" (1975).
  - Correspondence, 1899-1966 (Box 104, Folder 1)
  - Writings, 1891-1940 (Box 104, Folder 2-4)
  - Diaries, 1886-1898 (Box 104, Folder 5-8)
  - Diaries, 1900-1918, 1941-1946 (Box 105, Folder 9-12)
  - Appointment calendars, 1926-1931 (Box 105, Folder 13-15)
  - Appointment calendars, 1932-1933 (Box 106, Folder 16)
  - Souvenir book, 1882-1885 (Box 106, Folder 17)
  - Autograph book, 1887-1893 (Box 106, Folder 18)
  - Scrapbook, 1889-1891 (Box 106, Folder 19)
  - Notebook, 1895 (Box 106, Folder 20)
  - Address books, Undated (Box 106, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts, 1906-1960 (Box 106, Folder 22)
  - Wedding invitation of Alfreda Mitchell and Hiram Bingham; calling cards, 1900 November (Box 106, Folder 23)
  - Concert programs and certificate, 1900-1921 (Box 106, Folder 24)
  - Photographs (Box 106, Folder 25)
  - Financial records
    - Household details, engagement schedules, 1892-1926 (Box 106, Folder 26)
    - Will, 1960 (Box 106, Folder 27)
    - Notes concerning disposition of property, 1961 (Box 106, Folder 27)
    - Account books, 1897-1900, 1946-1965 (Box 107, Folder 28-29)
    - Budget books, 1941-1967 (Box 107, Folder 30-32)
    - Journal, 1937-1967 (Box 107, Folder 33)
    - Payrolls, 1964-1967 (Box 107, Folder 34)
    - Bills and receipts, 1900-1912 (Box 107, Folder 35)
  - Selections from the writings of others collected by Alfreda Mitchell, 1900 (Box 108, Folder 36)
  - Quotations and writings by others, Undated (Box 108, Folder 37)
  - Newsclippings, 1922-1937, undated (Box 108, Folder 38-45)
  - Bingham, Alfred M.
    - Articles and letters about family history, 1965-1975 (Box 108, Folder 46)
    - Articles, 1930, 1976 (Box 108, Folder 47)
    - Newsclippings, 1931-1935 (Box 108, Folder 48)
  - Bingham, Charles Tiffany: newsclippings, 1925-1928 (Box 108, Folder 49)
  - Bingham, Hiram IV, Brewster and Mitchell: newsclippings, 1930-1935 (Box 108, Folder 50)
  - Bingham, Hiram IV: scrapbooks, 1903-1915 (Box 109, Folder 51-52)
  - Bingham, Jonathan Brewster: drawing book, 1921-1922 (Box 109, Folder 53)
  - Bingham, Jonathan Brewster: newsclippings, 1933-1936 (Box 109, Folder 54)
  - Bingham, Woodbridge: newsclippings, 1927 (Box 109, Folder 55)
  - Bingham, Woodbridge: school papers, 1908-1968 (Box 109, Folder 56)
- Henry S. Gregor, 1894-1967; Series XI; 1; (2 boxes)
  Series XI, Henry S. Gregor, consists of papers of Alfreda (Mitchell) Bingham's second husband, Henry S. Gregor. His papers include: correspondence from Alfreda Bingham before their marriage, 1935-1937; general correspondence, 1906-1960; diaries, 1894-1895, 1938, 1951; appointment calendars, 1956-1957; notebooks, undated; legal correspondence, 1956-1964; legal, financial, and estate papers, 1957-1967; marriage certificate and papers, 1937; obituaries, 1964; concert programs, 1941-1956; anti-war cartoons, 1941; newsclippings, 1937-1964; and photographs.
  - Correspondence from Alfreda (Mitchell) Bingham, 1935-1937, undated (Box 110, Folder 1-4)
  - General correspondence, 1906-1960 (Box 110, Folder 5-6)
  - Correspondence about barking dogs, 1951-1956 (Box 110, Folder 7)
  - Diaries, 1894-1895, 1938, 1951 (Box 110, Folder 8)
  - Appointment calendar, 1956-1957 (Box 110, Folder 9-10)
  - Notebooks, Undated (Box 110, Folder 11)
  - Legal correspondence, 1956 October-1961 September (Box 110, Folder 12-14)
  - Legal correspondence, 1961 October-1964 (Box 111, Folder 15-17)
  - Correspondence concerning estate, 1965-1967 (Box 111, Folder 18)
  - Wills and codicils, 1957-1961 (Box 111, Folder 19)
  - Trust agreements; power of attorney; deeds, 1961 (Box 111, Folder 20)
  - Securities, 1961-1965 (Box 111, Folder 21)
  - Estate papers, 1960-1964 (Box 111, Folder 22)
  - Marriage certificate and papers, 1937 August 6 (Box 111, Folder 23)
  - Obituaries, 1964 January (Box 111, Folder 24)
  - Concert programs, 1941-1956 (Box 111, Folder 25)
  - Chamber music: programs and papers of benefit concert given with Alfreda M. Gregor, 1953 (Box 111, Folder 26)
  - Anti-war cartoons collected by Henry Gregor, 1941 (Box 111, Folder 27)
  - Newsclippings, 1937-1964 (Box 111, Folder 28)
  - Photographs (Box 111, Folder 29)
- Hiram Bingham IV, 1942-1945, 1972; Series XII
  - Correspondence, 1942-1945 (Box 112, Folder 1-3)
  - Writings
    - Balanced distribution ...by Carlos B. Rovere [i.e. Hiram Bingham IV] and Robert A. Rennie. n.p. 23p., 1943 (Box 112, Folder 4)
    - Proyecto de un nuevo mecanismo destinado a combatir la inflacion... (typescript carbon), 6 p., Undated (Box 112, Folder 4)
    - [On distribution], (typescript carbon), 6 p., Undated (Box 112, Folder 4)
    - [On Rudolf Steiner], (typescript mimeographed), 1 p., Undated (Box 112, Folder 5)
  - Business brochures - Sportatron, Inc., 1972, undated (Box 112, Folder 6)
- Index to Select Correspondents, Series I, II, III, General correspondence (Box 113)
- Additional Material, 1874-1984; Accession 1987-M-031
  Includes previous additions. The addition is comprised of five series: Correspondence, Family history, Personal, Writings, and Photographs. Most of the materials in the addition document some aspect of the life of Hiram Bingham III. There is valuable information concerning changing dynamics and shifting allegiances within his family over several decades. The marriage of Hiram and Alfreda Mitchell Bingham is well documented, from its beginning in 1900 to its demise in the 1930s. There is much documentation on Hiram Bingham III's various careers, especially his years in electoral politics and his chairmanship of President Truman's Loyalty Board, and his attendant political beliefs. There are interesting biographical narratives by Bingham family members which focus largely on Hiram Bingham III and his life accomplishments. Various writings convey Bingham's strongly held political beliefs and his general thinking on matters of government, especially as they involved some of the important debates of the first half of the twentieth century.
  - Correspondence, Series I
    This series, the largest in the addition, is organized into two sections: Family and General. Letters in the Family section are comprised of those written from one member of the Bingham family to another. They are organized alphabetically by sender and, subsequently, alphabetically by recipient. Among the Family letters, there are four main senders: Alfred Bingham, Alfreda Mitchell Bingham; Hiram Bingham III; and Woodbridge Bingham. The three largest sets of letters are those from Hiram Bingham III to his mother, Mrs. Hiram Bingham II; letters from Alfreda Mitchell Bingham to her son, Woodbridge Bingham; and letters from Hiram Bingham III to Woodbridge Bingham. The letters from Hiram Bingham III to Mrs. Hiram Bingham II cover the years from 1892 to 1903, which include the time Bingham spent as a student at Phillips Academy, Yale University, and Harvard University, and his marriage to Alfreda Mitchell in 1900. These letters impart a sense of Bingham's movement away from his strict religious upbringing and into varied, and generally more secular, social environments. His relationship with Alfreda Mitchell prior to their marriages, and a 1902 trip to Europe, are also among the subjects of Bingham's letters to his mother. The letters from Alfreda Mitchell Bingham to Woodbridge Bingham, written between 1927 and 1938, are largely routine, but some of the letters disclose information about the decline and eventual end of Hiram and Alfreda Mitchell Bingham's marriage. The letters from Hiram Bingham III to his first son, Woodbridge Bingham, range from 1914 to 1955. These letters too contain information about the Bingham divorce and other personal matters, but they also provide insights into Hiram Bingham III's public life. During these years, he was a Yale professor, governor of Connecticut, United States senator, president of the National Aeronautics Association, and chairman of President Harry Truman's Loyalty Board. In informal ways, the letters to his son express Bingham's political beliefs over several decades and his views of world events. In 1930, for instance, he writes about the amendments he introduced to the Volstead Act which sought to reduce the harshness of Prohibition regulations, and in the 1950s he writes in defense of his leadership of the Loyalty Board.
    The general section is arranged alphabetically and primarily contains letters between Hiram Bingham III and non-family members. Many of the letters involve Bingham's trip to China and the Far East in the late 1920s and detail the related foreign policy issues which concerned him. A 1910 document, written to members of the Carnegie Institution, is a proposal for the development of "scientific" studies of Central and South America.
    - Family
      - Bingham, Alfred, to
        - Bingham, Hiram, III, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Bingham, Hiram, III and Alfreda Mitchell Bingham, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        - Bingham, Woodbridge, 1927-1953 (Box 1, Folder 3-14)
      - Bingham, Alfreda Mitchell, to
        - Bingham, Bruce, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        - Bingham, Harry, 1925-1936 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
        - Bingham, Hiram, III, 1911-1916 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
        - Bingham, Woodbridge, 1927-1938 (Box 1, Folder 20-28)
      - Bingham, Hiram, III, to
        - Bingham, Alfreda Mitchell, 1911-1927 (Box 2, Folder 29-32)
        - Bingham, Bruce, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 33)
        - Bingham, Harry, 1924-1954 (Box 2, Folder 34-36)
        - Bingham, Hiram II, 1878-1891 (Box 2, Folder 37)
        - Bingham, Mrs. Hiram II, 1892-1897 (Box 2, Folder 38-44)
        - Bingham, Mrs. Hiram II, 1898-1903 (Box 3, Folder 45-54)
        - "Family" letters, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 55)
        - "Sons", 1915-1918 (Box 3, Folder 56-57)
        - Bingham, Woodbridge, 1914-1955 (Box 4, Folder 58-85)
        - Miscellaneous [childhood letters], 1880-1889 (Box 4, Folder 86)
      - Bingham, Woodbridge, to
        - Bingham, Alfred, 1961-1974 (Box 4, Folder 87)
        - Bingham, Alfreda Mitchell, 1931-1961 (Box 4, Folder 88-90)
        - Bingham, Hiram, III, 1924-1956 (Box 5, Folder 91-98)
        - "Brothers", 1954 (Box 5, Folder 99)
        - Miscellaneous, 1956-1979 (Box 5, Folder 100)
      - Other family members to
        - Bingham, Hiram, III, 1879-1899 (Box 5, Folder 101)
        - Bingham, Woodbridge, 1928-1937, undated (Box 5, Folder 102-106)
        - Miscellaneous, 1888-1934, undated (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - General
      - Bingham, Hiram, III
        - Carnegie Institution [proposal for research in Latin America], 1910 (Box 5, Folder 108)
        - Crist, Raymond, 1935-1936 (Box 5, Folder 109)
        - China/Far East trip [various recipients], 1927-1929 (Box 5, Folder 110-114)
        - Cunningham, Edwin S., 1927-1928 (Box 5, Folder 115-116)
        - Loyalty Board, 1951-1952 (Box 5, Folder 117)
        - Roosevelt, Theodore [several short, photocopied letters regarding Roosevelt's admiration for Bingham], 1916-1917 (Box 5, Folder 118)
        - Ta Kung-pao, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 119)
        - Yale University, 1899-1901, undated (Box 5, Folder 120)
        - Miscellaneous, 1915-1924 undated (Box 5, Folder 121)
      - Bingham, Woodbridge, 1924-1979 (Box 5, Folder 122)
  - Family history, Series II